A Guide to the Papers of Josephine Rucker Powell 1929-1996
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
Josephine Rucker Powell Papers 1929-1996
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
014
This collection is 9 cu. ft. in extent.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Information
Josephine Pierce Rucker Powell was born in Richmond, Virginia in 1911. She attended the Collegiate School for Girls and graduated from Sweet Briar College. She participated in multiple varsity sports excelling at swimming and diving. She was a model at Miller & Rhoads Department Store in Richmond and worked for three years in the office of her physician father Dr. Marvin P. Rucker.
In 1936 she married Lewis F. Powell Jr. They had four children. They lived in Richmond all their lives until Lewis Powell joined the U.S. Supreme Court in 1972. Thereafter, they maintained residences in both Washington and Richmond.
Active in community and cultural activities, Mrs. Powell was a member of The National Society for Colonial Dames of America in the Commonwealth of Virginia, the National Society of the Barons of Runnemede, the Sulgrave Club, International Neighbors Club #1 (president), Junior League of Richmond (vice president), board member of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Poe Foundation, Children's Theatre of Richmond Inc., Three Chopt Garden Club, and the Woman's Club. She died July 24, 1996.
Scope and Content Information
These papers document Josephine R. Powell's personal and social life. There is also a substantial record of the condolences extended to her family on her death and of her funeral service.
Arrangement
These papers have been preliminarily sorted into eleven series: Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Christmas Cards, Invitations, Postcards, Subject Files, Printed Materials, Photos, Clippings, Appointment Calendars,and Funeral. Several of the series have significant subseries components.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Manuscript Collections
Researchers should note that the Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Papers Ms 001, also at the Washington and Lee University School of Law, contain a substantial volume of correspondence and records by and about Josephine Rucker Powell and her immediate family. Note especially, that all of the voluminous correspondence between Josephine Powell and her husband Lewis, is in the Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Papers.
Contents List
- Biographical Materials, 1882-1996 (Carton 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1929-1996 (Carton 1)
  - Parents, 1932-1978 (Carton 2)
  - Children, 1955-1995 (Carton 2)
- Christmas Cards c. 1957-1995 (Carton 3)
  These Christmas cards complement those contained in the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, Ms 001.
- Invitations
  - General, c. 1955-1996 (Carton 4-5)
  - Supreme Court of the United States, 1972-1991 (Carton 5)
  - The White House, 1972-1988 (Carton 5)
  - Presidential Inauguration, 1973 (Carton 5)
- Postcards 1932-1948 (Carton 6)
  These postcards were apparently assembled by the donor as a collection of images. Most, however, bear messages. Some were addressed to the donor or members of her family. Others are to and from unknown third parties.
- Subject Files c. 1936-1984 (Carton 7-8)
  Subjects include: American Bar Association, 1961-1971; Auto Accident, 1966; Guest Lists; Notes re Justice Powell's Surgery, 1985; Poe Foundation/Old Stone House; Receipts; Recipes; Directories and Directions; Visit of Queen Mother, 1953; and Writings, 1965-1977.
- Printed Materials c. 1929-1995
  Forms of materials include: General Materials, Memorial Services, Menus, Place Cards, and school yearbooks (The Torch, 1929; Collegiate School for Girls. and The Briar Patch, 1933: Sweet Briar College.
- Photos, c.1929-1988 (Carton 8)
- Clippings, 1932-1983 (Carton 8)
- Appointment Calendars 1962-1993 (Carton 9)
- Funeral 1996 (Carton 10)